<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
        <title>Pedersen Laboratory</title>
        <description>Pedersen Laboratory - Nigel Pedersen</description>
        <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org/</link>
        <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org/</link>
        <lastBuildDate>2018-07-18T13:27:50-04:00</lastBuildDate>
        <pubDate>2018-07-18T13:27:50-04:00</pubDate>
        <ttl>1800</ttl>


        <item>
                <title>Stereotactic laser amygdalohippocampotomy for mesial temporal lobe epilepsy.</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;29420840&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To evaluate the outcomes 1 year and longer following stereotactic laser amygdalohippocampotomy for mesial temporal lobe epilepsy in a large series of patients treated over a 5-year period since introduction of this novel technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surgical outcomes of a consecutive series of 58 patients with mesial temporal lobe epilepsy who underwent the surgery at our institution with at least 12 months of follow-up were retrospectively evaluated. A subgroup analysis was performed comparing patients with and without mesial temporal sclerosis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One year following stereotactic laser amygdalohippocampotomy, 53.4% (95% confidence interval [CI] = 40.8-65.7%) of all patients were free of disabling seizures (Engel I). Three of 9 patients became seizure-free following repeat ablation. Subgroup analysis showed that 60.5% (95% CI = 45.6-73.7%) of patients with mesial temporal sclerosis were free of disabling seizures as compared to 33.3% (95% CI = 15.0-58.5%) of patients without mesial temporal sclerosis. Quality of Life in Epilepsy-31 scores significantly improved at the group level, few procedure-related complications were observed, and verbal memory outcome was better than historical open resection data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an unselected consecutive series of patients, stereotactic laser amygdalohippocampotomy yielded seizure-free rates for patients with mesial temporal lobe epilepsy lower than, but comparable to, the outcomes typically associated with open temporal lobe surgery. Analogous to results from open surgery, patients without mesial temporal sclerosis fared less well. This novel procedure is an effective minimally invasive alternative to resective surgery. In the minority of patients not free of disabling seizures, laser ablation presents no barrier to additional open surgery. Ann Neurol 2018;83:575-587.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/29420840</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/29420840</guid>
                <pubDate>2018-02-09T00:00:00-05:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Supramammillary glutamate neurons are a key node of the arousal system.</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;29123082&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basic and clinical observations suggest that the caudal hypothalamus comprises a key node of the ascending arousal system, but the cell types underlying this are not fully understood. Here we report that glutamate-releasing neurons of the supramammillary region (SuMvglut2) produce sustained behavioral and EEG arousal when chemogenetically activated. This effect is nearly abolished following selective genetic disruption of glutamate release from SuMvglut2 neurons. Inhibition of SuMvglut2 neurons decreases and fragments wake, also suppressing theta and gamma frequency EEG activity. SuMvglut2 neurons include a subpopulation containing both glutamate and GABA (SuMvgat/vglut2) and another also expressing nitric oxide synthase (SuMNos1/Vglut2). Activation of SuMvgat/vglut2 neurons produces minimal wake and optogenetic stimulation of SuMvgat/vglut2 terminals elicits monosynaptic release of both glutamate and GABA onto dentate granule cells. Activation of SuMNos1/Vglut2 neurons potently drives wakefulness, whereas inhibition reduces REM sleep theta activity. These results identify SuMvglut2 neurons as a key node of the wake-sleep regulatory system.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/29123082</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/29123082</guid>
                <pubDate>2017-11-11T00:00:00-05:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Join</title>
                <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;join-the-gutman-lab&quot;&gt;Join the Gutman Lab&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a number of ways that trainees and staff can join our lab and contribute to our mission, listed below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Graduate training&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Dr. Pedersen is affiliated with several programs at Emory University:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://biomed.emory.edu/PROGRAM_SITES/NS/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Emory Neuroscience Graduate Program&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research Fellows&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Interested post-doctoral fellows should send a cover letter and CV to&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:nigel.pedersen@emory.edu&quot;&gt;nigel.pedersen@emory.edu&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//misc/join</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//misc/join</guid>
                <pubDate>2017-10-17T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Welcome</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome! This is the new Gutman’s website, based off &lt;a href=&quot;http://bedford.io&quot;&gt;Trevor Bedford’s&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://drummondlab.org/about.html&quot;&gt;D. Allan Drummond’s&lt;/a&gt; website template.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//blog/welcome</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//blog/welcome</guid>
                <pubDate>2017-09-28T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Research</title>
                <description>
&lt;h2 id=&quot;epilepsy-and-systems-neuroscience&quot;&gt;Epilepsy and Systems Neuroscience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-10&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img width=&quot;500&quot; class=&quot;pull-right&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/research/pederson_pic.png&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;post&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;
			In our Epilepsy and Systems Neuroscience Laboratory, we study the systems neuroscience of wakefulness and epilepsy in humans and animal models. There are two main streams of research. The first centers on the neurobiological basis of consciousness and the underlying wake-sustaining mechanisms upon which it depends (1-6); another group of projects examines brain networks in epileptic seizures, including the modulatory effects of sleep-wake circuits and networks through which seizures propagate.

			&lt;p&gt; We study large-scale brain circuits underlying wakefulness and sleep. Using a variety of genetically encoded technologies in mice, we have recently described a new component of the brain circuit that maintains wakefulness, the supramammillary hypothalamus (3). This region exerts control over both the hippocampal network (important for certain kinds of memory formation) as well as the wake network and cerebral cortex. A unique and interesting feature of this neuronal group is the presence of a subpopulation of neurons that we described to release both inhibitory GABA and excitatory glutamate on to a key population of hippocampal neurons - dentate granule cells (3). These neurons are sparsely firing neurons that control which activity enters the classical hippocampal tri-synaptic circuit. The supramammillary region, comprising three major neuronal populations (3), is thus able to control wakefulness and influence information flow into the hippocampus. Studies continue to understand the role of these circuits on attention, wakefulness and the role of this region in setting hippocampal excitability in epilepsy. A specific ongoing experiment involves disruption of GABA release by supramammillary neurons and examining spontaneous seizures and seizure threshold, using Cre-lox techniques. We are also examining the anatomical connectivity and spontaneous activity of identified supramammillary neuronal subpopulations using unit recording and, later, fiber photometry.

			&lt;p&gt; Human work is presently centered on two major types of project, both involving our patients admitted for intracranial monitoring for epilepsy surgery. One group of projects examines a technique for neurophysiological identification of human cortical networks using single-pulse electrical stimulation, providing key clinical information as well the best means of determining human cortical networks (given the limits of diffusion tensor MRI). The other group of projects is centered on the study of consciousness. A key research goal of this program is to understand the top-down control of sleep-wake circuits and brain rhythms by the cerebral cortex in humans, using electrical stimulation of depth (SEEG) electrodes.

			&lt;p&gt; We are also developing techniques of the distributed recording of field potentials and unit activity in mice using a combination of tetrodes and high-resolution 3D resin printing of a micro-drive housing that can target specific widely distributed brain regions. This will allow us to obtain SEEG-like recordings in the mouse to examine ictal propagation and the role of subcortical structures in seizure semiology including in impairment of consciousness, respiratory abnormalities in seizures and post-ictal obtundation.

			&lt;p&gt; Presently our lab consists of a laboratory assistant, neurology resident, an Emory undergrad, one Georgia Tech undergrad and several collaborators.
			&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;bigspacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;spacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//misc/research</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//misc/research</guid>
                <pubDate>2017-08-08T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>The Gutman Lab</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;The Pedersen Lab at Emory University focuses on using novel techniques to answer important questions in neurosciences, with a focus on epilepsy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//misc/home</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//misc/home</guid>
                <pubDate>2017-08-08T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>About</title>
                <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-pedersen-lab&quot;&gt;The Pedersen Lab&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a background in clinical neurology, clinical epilepsy, neuroanatomy and the neurophysiology of epilepsy and sleep, we are poised to push forward the collective understanding of brain function in health and neurological conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Present projects are directed toward unstanding the relationship between brain structures important for sleep and wakefulness, and how these same structures determine the chance of having seizures.  We are also examining novel techniques to control seizures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please feel free to get involved or contact us for more information.  As an academic laboratory, teaching is part of our mission and students are always welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Affiliations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.neurology.emory.edu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dept of Neurology, Emory University&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://biomed.emory.edu/PROGRAM_SITES/NS/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dept of Neuroscience, Emory Unviersity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//misc/about</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//misc/about</guid>
                <pubDate>2017-08-08T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Naomie Gutekunst</title>
                <description>
</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//team/Naomie_LS</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//team/Naomie_LS</guid>
                <pubDate>2017-07-29T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Asmita Gathoo</title>
                <description>
</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//team/AsmitaN</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//team/AsmitaN</guid>
                <pubDate>2017-07-29T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Contact</title>
                <description>&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-6&quot;&gt;
        &lt;address&gt;
	&lt;b&gt; Department of Neurology &lt;/b&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
            6105 WMRB&lt;br /&gt;
            Emory University&lt;br /&gt;
            Atlanta, GA&lt;br /&gt;
            30322&lt;br /&gt;
            &lt;br /&gt;
	    Dr. Nigel Pedersen &lt;br /&gt;
            Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:nigel.pedersen@emory.edu&quot;&gt;nigel.pedersen@emory.edu&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
	    Twitter: &lt;a href=&quot;#&quot; onclick=&quot;window.open(&amp;quot;https://twitter.com/nigel.pedersen&amp;quot;);return false;&quot;&gt; @pedersenlab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	    &lt;br /&gt;
	    Argo Dalapati &lt;br /&gt;
	    Phone:+1 404.778.3444&lt;br /&gt;
	    Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:adalapa@emory.edu&quot;&gt;adalapa@emory.edu&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
        &lt;/address&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-6&quot;&gt;
        &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d2277.836368359841!2d-84.32338465139209!3d33.793216745530366!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x88f506fa0a36405b%3A0x17dc988a90d246a3!2sEmory+Woodruff+Memorial+Research+Building!5e0!3m2!1sen!2sus!4v1524419746276&quot; width=&quot;450&quot; height=&quot;450&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;border:0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;bigspacer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;col-md-12&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img class=&quot;center-block&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/WMRB.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//misc/contact</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//misc/contact</guid>
                <pubDate>2017-07-12T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Cluster Part 1</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;So given the constraints of my research budget, I did not (nor expect to have) $250,000+ to buy a new HPC cluster. While Cloud Computing is also exciting, and I’ll probably discuss some musings on that in a separate post, there’s a lot of unknown costs that make it hard for me to predict. One of the biggest challenges, is that my “base” data set is approximately 20 Terabytes. When I first started looking into this 4-5 years ago, storing that amount of data was prohibitively expensive. Even now, it’s not cheap…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I started off small, with a 16 core server with some hard drives. I used Sun Grid Engine (and now torque) to handle job execution, and have stuck with Ubuntu as my primary OS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first “BIG” purchase after this was a Storage NAS. I have been using QNAP devices for almost ten years, and have been a big fan. I like having at least some of my primary storage as an “appliance” . On multiple occasions I have fried my primary system during upgrades, installing software/etc.. and by having at least some of my files living in a stable spot (aka QNAP), I’ve saved myself a lot of frustration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the NAS was up and running, I purchased my first batch of servers. After spending a LOT of time searching around, I made a couple of executive decisions. While my head node and NAS were purchased new, for my compute cluster I basically wanted max # of CPU’s and memory for the least amount of money. One great option, particularly for a cash-strapped lab can do some of it’s own maintenance and doesn’t need to be truly production is to look into refurbished servers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first batch of servers included 10 HPG6 DL160 servers. I was able to purchase each machine for about $800.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HP ProLiant DL160 G6 1U 2x XEON HEX-CORE X5650 2.66GHz with 72GB DDR3. Each machine only had an 160GB drive for the primary OS, but that’s OK because everything was connected to my NAS which is where all the files lived. This was setup just using standard 1GB connectivity, and basically was able to rack all the machines fairly quickly…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Purchasing a similarly specced machine new would have cost me around $4000-$5000 each. The only downside, is that I don’t have any warranty (other than the 90 days from the vendor). However unless I have incredibly poor luck, if any of the machines wound up dying I’d still be WAY ahead. Also these aren’t the absolutely latest generation, but for bulk parallel computation, it doesn’t matter. Also the marginal improvement from generation to generation is not a factor of 10… it’s usually several percent increases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So basically, for an $8000 investment, I now purchased 120 cores (240 threads) of computing, and 720GB of RAM (72GB / server is quite nice).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now I just have a lot of “stuff”…. I need to actually get them provisioned/configured…. That’s in the next post…&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//blog/cluster</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//blog/cluster</guid>
                <pubDate>2016-09-29T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Lauren Aiani</title>
                <description>
</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//team/LGutekunst</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//team/LGutekunst</guid>
                <pubDate>2016-07-30T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Argo Dalapati</title>
                <description>
</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//team/Argo_Dalapati</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//team/Argo_Dalapati</guid>
                <pubDate>2016-07-29T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Basal forebrain control of wakefulness and cortical rhythms.</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;26524973&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wakefulness, along with fast cortical rhythms and associated cognition, depend on the basal forebrain (BF). BF cholinergic cell loss in dementia and the sedative effect of anti-cholinergic drugs have long implicated these neurons as important for cognition and wakefulness. The BF also contains intermingled inhibitory GABAergic and excitatory glutamatergic cell groups whose exact neurobiological roles are unclear. Here we show that genetically targeted chemogenetic activation of BF cholinergic or glutamatergic neurons in behaving mice produced significant effects on state consolidation and/or the electroencephalogram but had no effect on total wake. Similar activation of BF GABAergic neurons produced sustained wakefulness and high-frequency cortical rhythms, whereas chemogenetic inhibition increased sleep. Our findings reveal a major contribution of BF GABAergic neurons to wakefulness and the fast cortical rhythms associated with cognition. These findings may be clinically applicable to manipulations aimed at increasing forebrain activation in dementia and the minimally conscious state.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/26524973</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/26524973</guid>
                <pubDate>2015-11-04T00:00:00-05:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Adam Dickey</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Undergraduate Institution: Wake Forest University&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Medical School: University of Chicago&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PGY 1: Emory University School of Medicine&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Biography&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adam grew up in Danville, KY, and went to school at Wake Forest University in Winston-Salem, NC, where he studied Math and Economics.  He did research at Washington University in St. Louis for one year after graduation, and then went to University of Chicago for his MD and PhD. In grad school, he trained rhesus macaques to play video games, and contributed to a book called “Matlab for Neuroscientists.” In his free time, Adam Dickey likes to walk in the woods, watch Kentucky basketball and play Legos with his almost 4 year old son Isaac.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//team/adickey</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//team/adickey</guid>
                <pubDate>2015-07-11T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Jon T. Willie</title>
                <description>
</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//team/Jon_Willie</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//team/Jon_Willie</guid>
                <pubDate>2015-07-11T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>John Gale</title>
                <description>
</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//team/John_Gale</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//team/John_Gale</guid>
                <pubDate>2015-07-11T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Daniel Drane</title>
                <description>
</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//team/Daniel_Drane</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//team/Daniel_Drane</guid>
                <pubDate>2015-07-11T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Nigel Pedersen</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Dr. Pedersen graduated with First-Class Honors in Neuroscience from Flinders University before entering Sydney University Medical School where he also graduated with Honors. After completing medical school in Sydney, Australia, Dr. Pedersen moved to Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center in Boston for research training, followed by clinical training at Harvard Medical School at Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center, Boston Children’s Hospital and Massachusetts General Hospital. He was briefly on staff at Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center, Harvard Medical School, before being recruited to join Emory University and the Emory Comprehensive Epilepsy Program. Dr. Pedersen is passionate about discovery and innovation in epilepsy and aims to improve the lives of people with epilepsy. He runs a basic science laboratory at Emory University devoted to understanding the systems neuroscience of epilepsy and how this relates to sleep-wake brain circuits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our Epilepsy and Systems Neuroscience Laboratory, we study the systems neuroscience of wakefulness and epilepsy in humans and animal models. There are two main streams of research. The first centers on the neurobiological basis of consciousness and the underlying wake-sustaining mechanisms upon which it depends (1-6); another group of projects examines brain networks in epileptic seizures, including the modulatory effects of sleep-wake circuits and networks through which seizures propagate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We study large-scale brain circuits underlying wakefulness and sleep. Using a variety of genetically encoded technologies in mice, we have recently described a new component of the brain circuit that maintains wakefulness, the supramammillary hypothalamus (3). This region exerts control over both the hippocampal network (important for certain kinds of memory formation) as well as the wake network and cerebral cortex. A unique and interesting feature of this neuronal group is the presence of a subpopulation of neurons that we described to release both inhibitory GABA and excitatory glutamate on to a key population of hippocampal neurons - dentate granule cells (3). These neurons are sparsely firing neurons that control which activity enters the classical hippocampal tri-synaptic circuit. The supramammillary region, comprising three major neuronal populations (3), is thus able to control wakefulness and influence information flow into the hippocampus. Studies continue to understand the role of these circuits on attention, wakefulness and the role of this region in setting hippocampal excitability in epilepsy. A specific ongoing experiment involves disruption of GABA release by supramammillary neurons and examining spontaneous seizures and seizure threshold, using Cre-lox techniques. We are also examining the anatomical connectivity and spontaneous activity of identified supramammillary neuronal subpopulations using unit recording and, later, fiber photometry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Human work is presently centered on two major types of project, both involving our patients admitted for intracranial monitoring for epilepsy surgery. One group of projects examines a technique for neurophysiological identification of human cortical networks using single-pulse electrical stimulation, providing key clinical information as well the best means of determining human cortical networks (given the limits of diffusion tensor MRI). The other group of projects is centered on the study of consciousness. A key research goal of this program is to understand the top-down control of sleep-wake circuits and brain rhythms by the cerebral cortex in humans, using electrical stimulation of depth (SEEG) electrodes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also developing techniques of the distributed recording of field potentials and unit activity in mice using a combination of tetrodes and high-resolution 3D resin printing of a micro-drive housing that can target specific widely distributed brain regions. This will allow us to obtain SEEG-like recordings in the mouse to examine ictal propagation and the role of subcortical structures in seizure semiology including in impairment of consciousness, respiratory abnormalities in seizures and post-ictal obtundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other affiliations:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Assistant Professor, &lt;a href=&quot;http://med.emory.edu/index.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Neurology - Emory University&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Attending Neurologist, UBC &lt;a href=&quot;http://neurology.emory.edu/index.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Epilepsy Service, Emory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Principal Investigator, &lt;a href=&quot;http://epilepsylaboratory.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Epilepsy and Systems Neurobiology Lab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Full Member, SFU &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfu.ca/computing.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Program in Neuroscience, Emory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//team/Nigel_Pedersen</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//team/Nigel_Pedersen</guid>
                <pubDate>2015-07-10T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Trends in the management of headache.</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;25680354&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/25680354</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/25680354</guid>
                <pubDate>2015-02-15T00:00:00-05:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Trends in the ambulatory management of headache: analysis of NAMCS and NHAMCS data 1999-2010.</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;25567755&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Headache is a frequent complaint and among the most common reasons for visiting a physician.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To characterize trends from 1999 through 2010 in the management of headache.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Longitudinal trends analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nationally representative sample of visits to clinicians for headache from the National Ambulatory Medical Care Survey and National Hospital Ambulatory Medical Care Survey, excluding visits with “red flags,” such as neurologic deficit, cancer, or trauma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use of advanced imaging (CT/MRI), opioids/barbiturates, and referrals to other physicians (guideline-discordant indicators), as well as counseling on lifestyle modifications and use of preventive medications including verapamil, topiramate, amitriptyline, or propranolol (guideline-concordant during study period). We analyzed results using logistic regression, adjusting for patient and clinician characteristics, and weighted to reflect U.S. population estimates. Additionally, we stratified findings based on migraine versus non-migraine, acute versus chronic symptoms, and whether the clinician self-identified as the primary care physician.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We identified 9,362 visits for headache, representing an estimated 144 million visits during the study period. Nearly three-quarters of patients were female, and the mean age was approximately 46 years. Use of CT/MRI rose from 6.7% of visits in 1999-2000 to 13.9% in 2009-2010 (unadjusted p &amp;lt; 0.001), and referrals to other physicians increased from 6.9 % to 13.2% (p = 0.005). In contrast, clinician counseling declined from 23.5 % to 18.5% (p = 0.041). Use of preventive medications increased from 8.5 % to 15.9% (p = 0.001), while opioids/barbiturates remained unchanged, at approximately 18%. Adjusted trends were similar, as were results after stratifying by migraine versus non-migraine and acute versus chronic presentation. Primary care clinicians had lower odds of ordering CT/MRI (OR 0.56 [0.42, 0.74]).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrary to numerous guidelines, clinicians are increasingly ordering advanced imaging and referring to other physicians, and less frequently offering lifestyle counseling to their patients. The management of headache represents an important opportunity to improve the value of U.S. healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/25567755</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/25567755</guid>
                <pubDate>2015-01-09T00:00:00-05:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Glutamatergic signaling from the parabrachial nucleus plays a critical role in hypercapnic arousal.</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;23637157&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mechanisms of arousal from apneas during sleep in patients suffering from obstructive sleep apnea are not well understood. However, we know that respiratory chemosensory pathways converge on the parabrachial nucleus (PB), which sends glutamatergic projections to a variety of forebrain structures critical to arousal, including the basal forebrain, lateral hypothalamus, midline thalamus, and cerebral cortex. We tested the role of glutamatergic signaling in this pathway by developing an animal model for repetitive CO2 arousals (RCAs) and investigating the effect of deleting the gene for the vesicular glutamate transporter 2 (Vglut2) from neurons in the PB. We used mice with lox P sequences flanking exon2 of the Vglut2 gene, in which adeno-associated viral vectors containing genes encoding Cre recombinase and green fluorescent protein were microinjected into the PB to permanently and selectively disrupt Vglut2 expression while labeling the affected neurons. We recorded sleep in these mice and then investigated the arousals during RCA. Vglut2 deletions that included the external lateral and lateral crescent subdivisions of the lateral PB more than doubled the latency to arousal and resulted in failure to arouse by 30 s in &amp;gt;30% of trials. By contrast, deletions that involved the medial PB subdivision had minimal effects on arousal during hypercapnia but instead increased non-rapid eye movement (NREM) sleep by ∼43% during the dark period, and increased delta power in the EEG during NREM sleep by ∼50%. Our results suggest that glutamatergic neurons in the lateral PB are necessary for arousals from sleep in response to CO2, while medial PB glutamatergic neurons play an important role in promoting spontaneous waking.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/23637157</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/23637157</guid>
                <pubDate>2013-05-03T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Illusion of stroke: intravascular lymphomatosis.</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;22249564&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We describe an unusual case of cerebral intravascular lymphomatosis wherein the         patient presented with multiple embolic strokes predominantly in the posterior         circulation. Using this case as an illustration, we review the literature of this         malignancy, which consists of extranodal diffuse large B-cell lymphoma. For patients         with recurrent stroke-like events without cardiac risk factors, the accurate diagnosis         requires a high index of suspicion by the neurologist and a brain biopsy specimen         demonstrating lymphoma cells within the lumen of cerebral blood vessels.         Intravascular lymphomatosis can be treated with systemic chemotherapies, but the         response rate and pattern of relapse remain unknown.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/22249564</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/22249564</guid>
                <pubDate>2012-01-18T00:00:00-05:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Patrick M. Fuller</title>
                <description>
</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//team/Patrick_Fuller</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//team/Patrick_Fuller</guid>
                <pubDate>2011-08-11T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Marco Cielo</title>
                <description>
</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//team/Marco_Cielo</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//team/Marco_Cielo</guid>
                <pubDate>2011-08-11T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Opioid receptor modulation of GABAergic and serotonergic spinally projecting neurons of the rostral ventromedial medulla in mice.</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;21593395&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rostral ventromedial medulla (RVM) is an important site of opioid actions and forms part of an analgesic pathway that projects to the spinal cord. The neuronal mechanisms by which opioids act within this brain region remain unclear, particularly in relation to the neurotransmitters GABA and serotonin. In the present study, we examined serotonergic and GABAergic immunoreactivity, identified using immunohistochemistry for tryptophan hydroxylase (TPH) and glutamate decarboxylase (GAD), in combination with in vitro whole cell patch clamping to investigate the role of opioids on the mouse RVM with identified projections to the spinal cord. Tyr-d-Ala-Gly-N-Me-Phe-Gly-ol enkephalin (DAMGO) produced μ-opioid receptor-mediated outward currents in virtually all TPH-immunoreactive projecting neurons and GAD-immunoreactive nonprojecting neurons (87% and 86%). The other groups of RVM neurons displayed mixed responsiveness to DAMGO (40-68%). Deltorphin II and U-69593 produced δ- and κ-opioid receptor-mediated outward currents in smaller subpopulations of RVM neurons, with many of the δ-opioid responders forming a subpopulation of μ-opioid-sensitive GABAergic nonprojecting neurons. These findings are consistent with prior electrophysiological and anatomic studies in the rat RVM and indicate that both serotonergic and GABAergic RVM neurons mediate the actions of μ-opioids. Specifically, μ-opioids have a direct postsynaptic inhibitory influence over both GABAergic and serotonergic neurons, including those that project to the dorsal spinal cord.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/21593395</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/21593395</guid>
                <pubDate>2011-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Reassessment of the structural basis of the ascending arousal system.</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;21280045&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “ascending reticular activating system” theory proposed that neurons in the upper brainstem reticular formation projected to forebrain targets that promoted wakefulness. More recent formulations have emphasized that most neurons at the pontomesencephalic junction that participate in these pathways are actually in monoaminergic and cholinergic cell groups. However, cell-specific lesions of these cell groups have never been able to reproduce the deep coma seen after acute paramedian midbrain lesions that transect ascending axons at the caudal midbrain level. To determine whether the cortical afferents from the thalamus or the basal forebrain were more important in maintaining arousal, we first placed large cell-body-specific lesions in these targets. Surprisingly, extensive thalamic lesions had little effect on electroencephalographic (EEG) or behavioral measures of wakefulness or on c-Fos expression by cortical neurons during wakefulness. In contrast, animals with large basal forebrain lesions were behaviorally unresponsive and had a monotonous sub-1-Hz EEG, and little cortical c-Fos expression during continuous gentle handling. We then retrogradely labeled inputs to the basal forebrain from the upper brainstem, and found a substantial input from glutamatergic neurons in the parabrachial nucleus and adjacent precoeruleus area. Cell-specific lesions of the parabrachial-precoeruleus complex produced behavioral unresponsiveness, a monotonous sub-1-Hz cortical EEG, and loss of cortical c-Fos expression during gentle handling. These experiments indicate that in rats the reticulo-thalamo-cortical pathway may play a very limited role in behavioral or electrocortical arousal, whereas the projection from the parabrachial nucleus and precoeruleus region, relayed by the basal forebrain to the cerebral cortex, may be critical for this process.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/21280045</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/21280045</guid>
                <pubDate>2011-02-01T00:00:00-05:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Sleep state switching.</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;21172606&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We take for granted the ability to fall asleep or to snap out of sleep into wakefulness, but these changes in behavioral state require specific switching mechanisms in the brain that allow well-defined state transitions. In this review, we examine the basic circuitry underlying the regulation of sleep and wakefulness and discuss a theoretical framework wherein the interactions between reciprocal neuronal circuits enable relatively rapid and complete state transitions. We also review how homeostatic, circadian, and allostatic drives help regulate sleep state switching and discuss how breakdown of the switching mechanism may contribute to sleep disorders such as narcolepsy.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/21172606</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/21172606</guid>
                <pubDate>2010-12-22T00:00:00-05:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Locus ceruleus and anterior cingulate cortex sustain wakefulness in a novel environment.</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;20980612&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Locus ceruleus (LC) neuronal activity is correlated with the waking state, yet LC lesions produce only minor alterations in daily wakefulness. Here, we report that sustained elevations in neurobehavioral and EEG arousal in response to exposure to an environment with novel stimuli, including social interaction, are prevented by selective chemical lesions of the LC in rats. Similar results are seen when the anterior cingulate cortex (ACC), which receives especially dense LC innervation, is selectively denervated of LC input or is ablated by the cell-specific neurotoxin ibotenic acid. Anterograde tracing combined with tyrosine hydroxylase immunohistochemistry demonstrates ACC terminals in apposition with the distal dendrites of LC neurons. Our data implicate the ACC as both a source of input to the LC as well as one of its targets and suggests that the two structures engage in a dialog that may provide a critical neurobiological substrate for sustained attention.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/20980612</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/20980612</guid>
                <pubDate>2010-10-29T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Brainstem circuitry regulating phasic activation of trigeminal motoneurons during REM sleep.</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;20098748&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rapid eye movement sleep (REMS) is characterized by activation of the cortical and hippocampal electroencephalogram (EEG) and atonia of non-respiratory muscles with superimposed phasic activity or twitching, particularly of cranial muscles such as those of the eye, tongue, face and jaw. While phasic activity is a characteristic feature of REMS, the neural substrates driving this activity remain unresolved. Here we investigated the neural circuits underlying masseter (jaw) phasic activity during REMS. The trigeminal motor nucleus (Mo5), which controls masseter motor function, receives glutamatergic inputs mainly from the parvocellular reticular formation (PCRt), but also from the adjacent paramedian reticular area (PMnR). On the other hand, the Mo5 and PCRt do not receive direct input from the sublaterodorsal (SLD) nucleus, a brainstem region critical for REMS atonia of postural muscles. We hypothesized that the PCRt-PMnR, but not the SLD, regulates masseter phasic activity during REMS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To test our hypothesis, we measured masseter electromyogram (EMG), neck muscle EMG, electrooculogram (EOG) and EEG in rats with cell-body specific lesions of the SLD, PMnR, and PCRt. Bilateral lesions of the PMnR and rostral PCRt (rPCRt), but not the caudal PCRt or SLD, reduced and eliminated REMS phasic activity of the masseter, respectively. Lesions of the PMnR and rPCRt did not, however, alter the neck EMG or EOG. To determine if rPCRt neurons use glutamate to control masseter phasic movements, we selectively blocked glutamate release by rPCRt neurons using a Cre-lox mouse system. Genetic disruption of glutamate neurotransmission by rPCRt neurons blocked masseter phasic activity during REMS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These results indicate that (1) premotor glutamatergic neurons in the medullary rPCRt and PMnR are involved in generating phasic activity in the masseter muscles, but not phasic eye movements, during REMS; and (2) separate brainstem neural circuits control postural and cranial muscle phasic activity during REMS.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/20098748</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/20098748</guid>
                <pubDate>2010-01-26T00:00:00-05:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>In the flicker of an eye.</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;18625803&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/18625803</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/18625803</guid>
                <pubDate>2008-07-16T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Do enteric neurons make hypocretin?</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;18191238&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hypocretins (orexins) are wake-promoting neuropeptides produced by hypothalamic neurons. These hypocretin-producing cells are lost in people with narcolepsy, possibly due to an autoimmune attack. Prior studies described hypocretin neurons in the enteric nervous system, and these cells could be an additional target of an autoimmune process. We sought to determine whether enteric hypocretin neurons are lost in narcoleptic subjects. Even though we tried several methods (including whole mounts, sectioned tissue, pre-treatment of mice with colchicine, and the use of various primary antisera), we could not identify hypocretin-producing cells in enteric nervous tissue collected from mice or normal human subjects. These results raise doubts about whether enteric neurons produce hypocretin.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/18191238</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/18191238</guid>
                <pubDate>2008-01-15T00:00:00-05:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Enhanced Fos expression in glutamic acid decarboxylase immunoreactive neurons of the mouse periaqueductal grey during opioid withdrawal.</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;16359817&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous studies using c-Fos immunohistochemistry suggest that a sub-population of neurons in the midbrain periaqueductal gray region is activated during opioid withdrawal. The neurochemical identity of these cells is unknown but cellular physiological studies have implicated GABAergic neurons. The present study investigated whether GABAergic neurons are activated in the mouse periaqueductal gray during opioid withdrawal using dual-antibody immunohistochemistry for Fos and glutamic acid decarboxylase. Both chronic opioid treatment and naloxone-precipitated opioid withdrawal increased Fos expression in the periaqueductal gray, with the greatest increase being four-fold in the caudal ventrolateral subdivision following withdrawal. Neurons stained for both Fos and glutamic acid decarboxylase were greatly enhanced in all subdivisions of the periaqueductal gray following withdrawal, particularly in the lateral and ventrolateral divisions where the increase was up to 70-fold. These results suggest that activation of a subpopulation of GABAergic interneurons in the periaqueductal gray plays a role in opioid withdrawal.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/16359817</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/16359817</guid>
                <pubDate>2005-12-20T00:00:00-05:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Clozapine reverses hyperthermia and sympathetically mediated cutaneous vasoconstriction induced by 3,4-methylenedioxymethamphetamine (ecstasy) in rabbits and rats.</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;12867524&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life-threatening hyperthermia occurs in some individuals taking 3,4-methylenedioxymethamphetamine (MDMA, ecstasy). In rabbits, sympathetically mediated vasoconstriction in heat-exchanging cutaneous beds (ear pinnae) contributes to MDMA-elicited hyperthermia. We investigated whether MDMA-elicited cutaneous vasoconstriction and hyperthermia are reversed by clozapine and olanzapine, atypical antipsychotic agents. Ear pinna blood flow and body temperature were measured in conscious rabbits; MDMA (6 mg/kg, i.v.) was administered; and clozapine (0.1-5 mg/kg, i.v.) or olanzapine (0.5 mg/kg, i.v.) was administered 15 min later. One hour after MDMA, temperature was 38.7 +/- 0.5 degrees C in 5 mg/kg clozapine-treated rabbits and 39.0 +/- 0.2 degrees C in olanzapine-treated rabbits, less than untreated animals (41.5 +/- 0.3 degrees C) and unchanged from pre-MDMA values. Ear pinna blood flow increased from the MDMA-induced near zero level within 5 min of clozapine or olanzapine administration. Clozapine-induced temperature and flow responses were dose-dependent. In urethane-anesthetized rabbits, MDMA (6 mg/kg, i.v.) increased ear pinna postganglionic sympathetic nerve discharge to 217 +/- 33% of the pre-MDMA baseline. Five minutes after clozapine (1 mg/kg, i.v.) discharge was reduced to 10 +/- 4% of the MDMA-elicited level. In conscious rats made hyperthermic by MDMA (10 mg/kg, s.c.), body temperature 1 hr after clozapine (3 mg/kg, s.c.) was 36.9 +/- 0.5 degrees C, &amp;lt;38.6 +/- 0.3 degrees C (Ringer’s solution-treated) and not different from the pre-MDMA level. One hour after clozapine, rat tail blood flow was 24 +/- 3 cm/sec, greater than both flow in Ringer’s solution-treated rats (8 +/- 1 cm/sec) and the pre-MDMA level (17 +/- 1 cm/sec). Clozapine and olanzapine, by interactions with 5-HT receptors or by other mechanisms, could reverse potentially fatal hyperthermia and cutaneous vasoconstriction occurring in some humans after ingestion of MDMA.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/12867524</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/12867524</guid>
                <pubDate>2003-07-18T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Cutaneous vasoconstriction contributes to hyperthermia induced by 3,4-methylenedioxymethamphetamine (ecstasy) in conscious rabbits.</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;11606652&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3,4-Methylenedioxymethamphetamine (MDMA; “Ecstasy”) increases body temperature. This process could be associated with increased cutaneous blood flow, as normally occurs with exercise-induced hyperthermia. Alternatively, an MDMA-induced fall in cutaneous blood flow could contribute to the hyperthermia by diminishing normal heat transfer from the body to the environment. We investigated these possibilities by administering MDMA (1.5-6 mg/kg, i.v.) to conscious freely moving rabbits, determining effects on body temperature, cutaneous blood flow (measured by a Doppler ultrasonic probe that was chronically implanted around the ear pinna artery), and other cardiovascular parameters. MDMA caused a dose-dependent increase in body temperature (from 38.3 +/- 0.3 to 41.2 +/- 0.4 degrees C after 6 mg/kg; p &amp;lt; 0.01; n = 5), preceded and accompanied by a dose-dependent cutaneous vasoconstriction (from 29 +/- 6 to 5 +/- 1 cm/sec after 6 mg/kg; p &amp;lt; 0.01; n = 5). MDMA (3 mg/kg) did not change blood flow to the mesenteric vascular bed. Prior unilateral cervical sympathectomy reduced the increase in body temperature elicited by MDMA (6 mg/kg) from 2.0 +/- 0.2 to 1.3 +/- 0.2 degrees C (p &amp;lt; 0.01; n = 5). On the denervated side, ear pinna blood flow after MDMA injection was 13 +/- 3 cm/sec, compared with 3 +/- 1 cm/sec on the sympathetically intact side (p &amp;lt; 0.05; n = 5). Thus, sympathetically mediated cutaneous vasoconstriction is one mechanism whereby MDMA causes hyperthermia. Reversal of cutaneous vasoconstriction by appropriate pharmacological means could be of therapeutic benefit in humans suffering from life-threatening hyperthermia induced by MDMA.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/11606652</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/11606652</guid>
                <pubDate>2001-10-19T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>Tail artery blood flow measured by chronically implanted Doppler ultrasonic probes in unrestrained conscious rats.</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;11164247&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We describe a surgical procedure for chronically implanting a Doppler ultrasonic probe around the tail artery of the rat to measure phasic flow velocity in the tail artery of the unrestrained conscious rat. The phasic tail flow signal is highly correlated with the simultaneously recorded superior mesenteric flow signal (range 0.70-0.89 in seven rats) during vasoconstriction induced by exposure to formaldehyde vapour. In response to two quick alerting taps on the cage, tail flow velocity fell from 20+/-2 to 7+/-1 cm/s (P&amp;lt;0.01) and mesenteric flow fell from 30+/-5 to 25+/-4 cm/s (P&amp;lt;0.05), with the fall in tail flow being significantly greater than the fall in mesenteric flow (P&amp;lt;0.05, n=7 rats). In anesthetized rats, the phasic tail flow signal was highly correlated with phasic arterial pressure (range 0.71-0.83 in seven rats). The ability to reliably measure phasic arterial tail flow in the conscious unrestrained rat should facilitate experimental studies of brain pathways regulating flow to this principally cutaneous vascular bed in different physiological situations.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/11164247</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/11164247</guid>
                <pubDate>2001-02-13T00:00:00-05:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>[Mammography--watch out for false negatives].</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;2020948&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patients with breast tumours should be examined by a combination of physical examination, mammography and fine needle aspiration biopsy. The authors discuss the history of four patients with palpable breast lesions. All of these patients had tumours which had not been discovered by mammography. The diagnosis was delayed 2,11,12 and 12 months respectively. Patients with palpable lesions must not be referred to mammography performed under “screening conditions”, but must be examined in a clinical context, preferably by the “triple-test”.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/2020948</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/2020948</guid>
                <pubDate>1991-03-10T00:00:00-05:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>A rat model of psychopathology for use in exercise science.</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-popover=&quot;right&quot; data-badge-type=&quot;donut&quot; data-pmid=&quot;7070264&quot; data-hide-no-mentions=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;altmetric-embed&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exploratory behavior, defecation, urination, and a subjective psychophysical rating system were evaluated in a series of four experiments designed to assess rat psychopathology. In every case, individual rats were studied for 5-min periods in an open field consisting of 49 7.5-inch squares. We find that the open-field test can be scored in a highly objective manner (r = 0.93-0.98) by two observers. The reproducibility (r = 0.79-0.85) of the assessment using total squares traversed is not improved using any of the other parameters evaluated. Use of total squares alone was also found to be in agreement with a subjective behavioral rating procedure (r = 0.96-0.98). Fifty percent of overall variability occurs in a rat’s first trial. Therefore, the average of total squares traversed on the second and third (not necessarily consecutive) days provides a reliable and objective index of a rat’s emotional status. Using this criterion, we find that a random group of 30 adult, male Sprague-Dawley rats exhibit a range of psychopathologies. We propose that this method of assessment provides a rat model of emotionality which should theoretically be modifiable by experimental paradigms involving exercise and pharmacological or dietary intervention.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <link>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/7070264</link>
                <guid>http://epilepsylaboratory.org//papers/7070264</guid>
                <pubDate>1982-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</pubDate>
        </item>


</channel>
</rss>
